A fact
خرجت فكرة ..
came out of MIT,
من معهد " ام اي تي "
couple of years ago. Ken Hale,
منذ سنتين .. حيث قال " كين هال "
who's a linguist,
وهو عالم لغات
said that of the 6,000 languages
ان ال 6 الآلف التي ...
spoken on Earth right now,
يتم التحدث بها اليوم
3,000 aren't spoken by the children.
3 الآف منها لم يتعلمها الاطفال
So that in one generation,
أي خلال جيل واحد
we're going to halve our cultural diversity.
ثقافتنا البشرية ستنخفض الى النصف
He went on to say
وأضاف الى قوله السابق
that every two weeks,
انه كُل أسبوعين ..
an elder goes to the grave
يموت " كهل " ..
carrying the last spoken word
حاملا معه آخر كلمات ...
of that culture.
ثقافته ..
So an entire philosophy,
وبالتالي فان فلسفة كاملة تختفي
a body of knowledge about the natural world
وكمية معلومات وخبرات عن العالم الطبيعي
that had been empirically gleaned over centuries,
والتي تم جمعها عبر قرون عن طريق المراقبة والتجريب
goes away.
تندثر معه !
And this happens every two weeks.
وهذا يحدث كل اسبوعين .
So for the last 20 years,
لذا فان للسنوات ال 20 الماضية
since my dental experience,
منذ أن تركت طب الاسنان
I have been traveling the world
وانا اجول العالم .
and coming back
وأعود ..
with stories about some of these people.
بقصص عن هؤلاء الاشخاص
What I'd like to do right now
والذي أريد ان أقوم به اليوم " الآن "
is share some of those stories with you.
هو مشاركتكم هذه القصص
This is Tamdin.
هذه " تامدين "
She is a 69-year-old nun.
وهي راهبة تبلغ من العمر 69 عاماً
She was thrown in prison in Tibet for two years
تم زجها في السجن لمدة عامين في التيبت
for putting up a little tiny placard
لارتدائها " لافتة " صغيرة
protesting the occupation of her country.
اعتراضا على احتلال بلدها
And when I met her, she had just
وعندما قابلتها . كانت قد ..
taken a walk over the Himalayas
سارت على الاقدام عبر الهمالايا
from Lhasa, the capital of Tibet,
من مدينة لاسا " عاصمة التيبت "
into Nepal, across to India --
الى النيبال .. عبر الهند ..
30 days --
لمدة 30 يوماً
to meet her leader, the Dalai Lama.
لملاقات قائدها " الدلالي لاما "
The Dalai Lama lives in Dharamsala, India.
والذي يقطن في " دهارامسلا " في الهند
So I took this picture three days
وقد التقطت هذه الصورة بعد 3 ايام ..
after she arrived,
من وصولها
and she had this beat-up pair of tennis shoes on,
وكانت ترتدي هذه الاحضية الرياضية
with her toes sticking out.
وأصابعها تظهر منها ...
And she crossed in March,
وكانت قد عبر الطريق المذكور في شهر مارس
and there's a lot of snow at 18,500 feet in March.
وفي ذلك الوقت يكون هنالك الكثير من الثلوج على ارتفاع 18500 قدم
This is Paldin.
هذا "بالدين "
Paldin is a 62-year-old monk.
بالدين هو راهب عمره 62 عاما
And he spent 33 years in prison.
قضى 33 منها في السجن
His whole monastery was thrown into prison
وقد كان ... جُل فترة تعليمه الديني كانت في ذلك السجن
at the time of the uprising,
في فترة التصعيد ..
when the Dalai Lama had to leave
عندما اضطر الدلالي لاما الى الرحيل
Tibet.
الى التيبت
And
وهناك ..
he was beaten, starved,
تم ضربه .. وتجويعه ...
tortured -- lost all his teeth while in prison.
وتعذيبه .. وقد فقد كل اسنانه نتيجة لذلك في السجن
And when I met him, he was a kind gentle old man.
وعندما قابلته .. كان هذا المسن رجلا لطيفاً
And it really impressed me --
وقد أذهلني فعلاً
I met him two weeks after he got out of prison --
فقد قابلته بعد اسبوعين من خروجه من السجن
that he went through that experience, and ended up
خاصة بعد تلك التجربة والتي خرج منها ..
with the demeanor that he had.
بهذا السلوك الهادىء الذي يمتلكه
So I was in Dharamsala meeting these people,
إذا لقد كنت في " دهارامسلا " اقابل هؤلاء الاشخاص
and I'd spent about five weeks there,
وقد قضيت هنالك مايقارب الخمس أسابيع
and I was hearing these similar stories
أستمع الى قصص مماثلة لهذه القصص
of these refugees that had poured out of Tibet
عن هؤلاء اللاجئين القادمين من التيبت
into Dharamsala.
الى "دهارامسلا "
And it just so happened, on the fifth week,
وتماما في تلك الآونة وفي الاسبوع الخامس
there was a public teaching by the Dalai Lama.
كان هنالك درس " عام " للدلالي لاما
And
و ..
I was watching this crowd of monks and nuns,
عندما كنت أشاهد هذا الجمع الغفير من الرهبان والراهبات
many of which I had just interviewed,
والذي قابلت العديد منهم
and heard their stories,
واستمعت لقصصهم
and I watched their faces,
ونظرت الى وجوههم
and they gave us a little FM radio,
والذين أعطوني " راديو اف ام " صغير
and we could listen to the translation of his teachings.
لكي استطيع الاستماع الى ترجمة تعاليم " الدلالي لاما "
And what he said was:
والتي كانت تقول ..
treat your enemies as if they were precious jewels,
" عاملوا أعدائكم كما لو أنهم قطع مجوهرات ثمينة "
because it's your enemies
" لان أعدائكم ..
that build your tolerance and patience
هو الذين يصنعون صبركم واتزانكم ..
on the road to your enlightenment.
في طريقكم نحو النورانية "
That hit me so hard,
وقد صدمني هذا بشدة ..
telling these people that had been through this experience.
أي اخبار الناس بهذا بعد كل ما عانوه ..
So, two months later, I went into
وبعد شهرين لاحقا ذهبت الى ..
Tibet, and I started
التيبت وبدأت
interviewing the people there, taking my photographs. That's what I do.
أقابل الناس هناك .. وأأخذ بعض الصور لهم " هذا ما أفعله "
I interview and do portraits.
أقابل الناس وأأخذ الصور لهم
And this is a little girl.
وهنا في الصورة طفلة صغيرة
I took her portrait up on top of the Jokhang Temple.
ألتقطتها على قمة معبد " جوخانج "
And I'd snuck in --
وكنت قد أدخلت خلسة ..
because it's totally illegal to have a picture of the Dalai Lama in Tibet --
بعض الصور للدلالي لاما لانه ممنوع القيام بذلك في التيبت
it's the quickest way you can get arrested.
وهي الطريقة الاسرع لكي يتم القاء القبض عليك ..
So I snuck in a bunch of little wallet-sized pictures of the Dalai Lama,
لذا " ادخلت خلسة " بعض الصور الصغيرة بحجم المحفظة للدلالي لاما
and I would hand them out.
وكنت اسلمها لهؤلاء الاشخاص
And when I gave them to the people,
وعندما كنت اعطيهم إياها
they'd either hold them to their heart,
فهم إما يضعوها على قلوبهم ..
or they'd hold them up to their head and just stay there.
أو يرفعوها الى جباههم ويتركوها كذلك ..
And this is --
وهذه هي الصورة ..
well, at the time -- I did this 10 years ago --
وقد قمت بالتقاطها منذ 10 سنوات وكان في ذلك الوقت
that was 36 years after the Dalai Lama had left.
قد مضى 36 عاما على رحيل الدلالي لاما
So
...
I was going in, interviewing these people and doing their portraits.
كنت أجول هناك وأحاور الناس وأصورهم
This is Jigme and her sister, Sonam.
هذه " جيجم " وأختها " سونام "
And they live up on the Chang Tang, the Tibetan Plateau,
وهم يقطنون في " شانج تانغ " هضبة التيبت
way in the western part of the country.
نحو .. القسم الغربي من البلاد
This is at 17,000 feet.
على ارتفاع 17000 قدم
And they had just come down from the high pastures,
وقد كانوا قد هبطوا من أعلى الهضبة
at 18,000 feet.
أي من ارتفاع 18000 قدم
Same thing: gave her a picture,
ونفس الامر عندما أعطيتها الصورة
she held it up to her forehead.
وضعتها على جبتها
And I usually hand out Polaroids
وأنا اعطيهم عادة " صور فورية "
when I do these, because I'm setting up lights,
وعندما قمت بذلك .. وكنت أهيء الاضائة
and checking my lights,
وأُعد الانوار
and when I showed her her Polaroid, she screamed and ran into her tent.
فعندما رأت هذه الصورة الفورية " صرخت , وجرت الى خيمتها ..
This is Tenzin Gyatso;
هذا هو " تينزين جياتسو "
he was found to be the Buddha of Compassion at the age of two,
وقد تم اختياره كبوذا " التراحم " عندما كان في الثانية من عمره
out in a peasant's house,
في منزل أحد المزارعين
way out in the middle of nowhere.
في مكان مجهول تماما
At the age of four, he was installed
وفي عامه الرابع تم تعينه
as the 14th Dalai Lama.
ك الدلالي لاما الرابع عشر
As a teenager, he faced
وفي فترة مراهقته واجهت ..
the invasion of his country,
بلاده الغزو ..
and had to deal with it -- he was the leader of the country.
وكان يتوجب عليه التعامل مع هذا .. لانه كان قائد بلده
Eight years later, when they discovered there was a plot
وبعد ثمان سنوات من ذلك تم الكشف عن مكيدة
to kill him,
لإغتياله
they dressed him up like a beggar
فتم إلباسه لباس المتسولين
and snuck him out of the country on horseback,
وتهريبه خارج البلاد على ظهر حصان ..
and took the same trip that Tamdin did.
ليقوم بنفس الرحلة التي قامت بها " تاميدين "
And he's never been back to his country since.
ومنذ ذلك الحين لم يعد الى بلده
And
و ..
if you think about this man,
بالنظر الى هذا الرجل
46 years later,
وبعد 46 سنة
still sticking
فهو مازال متمسكاً
to this non-violent response
بخيار الرد السلمي
to a severe political and human rights issue.
لخدمة القضايا الانسانية والسياسية ..
And the young people,
وشباب التيبت
young Tibetans, are starting to say, listen, this doesn't work.
شباب التيبت يقولون " ان هذا لايُجدي نفعاً "
You know, violence as a political tool
كما تعلمون فالعنف أيضا أداة سياسية ..
is all the rage right now.
والغضب اليوم يملأ المكان هنا تماما ..
And
و هو
he still is holding this line.
مازال .. متمسكاً بقراره .
So this is our icon
لذا فهو قدوتنا .
to non-violence in our world --
لعالم سلمي ..
one of our living icons.
هو واحد من الرموز التي مازالت على قيد الحياة .
This is another leader of his people.
وهذا قائد آخر لشعبه
This is Moi. This is in the Ecuadorian Amazon.
أسمه " موي " وهنا هي الغابات الاكوادورية
And Moi is 35 years old.
و " موي " عمره 35 عاماً
And
و ..
this area of the Ecuadorian Amazon --
في هذه المنطقة من الغابات الاكوادورية
oil was discovered in 1972.
تم اكتشاف النفط عام 1972
And in this period of time -- since that time --
وفي ذلك الوقت من الزمن - وحتى اليوم -
as much oil, or twice as much oil
تسرب ما يقارب ضعفي كمية
as was spilled in the Exxon Valdez accident,
النفط التي تسربت في حادثة " اكسون فاديز "
was spilled in this little area of the Amazon,
على هذه الارض الصغير من الغابة
and the tribes in this area have constantly had to move.
واضطرت القبائل هناك مرارا وتكرار ان تنتقل ..
And Moi
و " موي "
belongs to the Huaorani tribe,
ينتمي الى قبيلة " هاوراني "
and they're known as
وهم معرفون بأنهم
very fierce, they're known as "auca."
عدائيون جداً ويطلق عليهم " اوكا "
And they've managed to keep out
وقد أستطاعوا ان يبقوا ..
the seismologists and the oil workers
علماء الأرض و عمال النفط بعيداً
with spears and blowguns.
بواسطة حرابهم و بنادقهم
And we spent --
وقد قضيت ..
I was with a team --
انا و فريقي ..
two weeks with these guys out in the jungle
أسبوعين مع هؤلاء الاشخاص في الغابة
watching them hunt.
نراقبهم وهم يصطادون
This was on a monkey hunt,
وقد شهدنا اصطياد " قرد "
hunting with curare-tipped darts.
بواسطة عصي تحمل سهاماً
And the knowledge that these people have
والمعرفة التي يملكها هؤلاء الأشخاص
about the natural environment is incredible.
عن البيئة الطبيعية هي مذهلة
They could hear things, smell things, see things I couldn't see.
حيث يمكنهم ان " يسمعوا اصواتا " ويشتموا روائح لا استطيع انا ذلك ..
And I couldn't even see the monkeys
لدرجة اني لم اكن أرى القردة ..
that they were
التي كانوا ..
getting with these darts.
يصطادونها بواسطة السهام .
This is Yadira,
هذه هي " ياديرا "
and Yadira is
وياديرا هي
five years old. She's in a
ابنة خمسة أعوام وتعيش مع
tribe that's neighboring the Huaorani.
قبيلة بجوار قبيلة " هاوراني "
And her tribe has had to move
وقد اضطرت قبيلتها للرحيل ..
three times in the last 10 years because of the oil spills.
3 مرات خلال العشر سنوات المنصرمة
And we never hear about that. And the latest
ولم يسمع أحدٌ عن هذا , وقد كان آخر
infraction against these people is,
اعتداء على هؤلاء الأشخاص ..
as part of Plan Colombia,
كجزء من خطة كولومبيا
we're spraying Paraquat or Round Up, whatever it is --
حيث قمنا برش المبيدات .. او تدويرها .. او نحو ذلك
we're defoliating thousands of acres
وجردنا ودمرنا آلاف من الدونمات
of the Ecuadorian Amazon
من الغابات الاكوادورية
in our war on drugs.
في حربنا ضد المخدرات .
And these people are the people who take the brunt of it.
وهؤلاء الاشخاص هم اللذين تضرروا من جراء ذلك .
This is Mengatoue.
وهذا هو " مينجاتوو"
He's the shaman of the Huaorani,
وهو حكيم قبيلة " هاوراني "
and
وهو ..
he said to us, you know, I'm an older man now;
لقد قال لنا " أتعلمون لقد غدوت رجلا كبيرا في السن ..
I'm getting tired, you know; I'm tired
وقد تعبت .. تعبت فعلاً ...
of spearing these oil workers.
من رمي الحراب على عمال النفط هؤلاء ..
I wish they would just go away.
لكم أتمنى أن يذهبوا بعيداً "
And I was -- I usually travel alone
وانا عادة اسافر بمفردي ..
when I do my work, but I did this --
عندما أقوم بعملي .. ولكن قمت بهذه الرحلة
I hosted a program for Discovery,
كمقدم لبرنامج على قناة " ديسكوفري "
and when I went down with the team,
وعندما وصلت هنالك مع الفريق
I was quite concerned about
كنت قلقاً قليلاً ..
going in with a whole bunch of people, especially into the Huaorani,
من قدوم مجموعة بعددنا , خاصة مع قبيلة مثل " هاوراني "
deep into the Huaorani tribe.
أي للعيش مع قبيلة " هاوراني "
And
و ..
as it turned out, these guys really
كما تبين لاحقاً , فقد علمني هؤلاء الرجال ..
taught me a thing or two about blending in
امراً أو إثنين عن كيفية الاندماج فعلاً
with the locals.
مع السكان الأصلين
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
One of the things I did
إحدى الأشياء التي قمت بها ..
just before 9/11 --
قبل الحادي عشر من سبتمبر/أيلول
August of 2001 --
تحديداً في أغسطس من عام 2001
I took my son, Dax,
أخذت إبني " داكس "
who was 16 at the time,
والذي كان يبلغ من العمر حينها 16 عاماً
and I took him to Pakistan.
أخذته الى باكستان
Because at first I wanted --
لانني أولا كنت أرغب
you know, I've taken him on a couple of trips,
كما تعلمون ... , اخذته الى قبيلتان
but I wanted him to see
أردته أن يرى ..
people that live on a dollar a day or less.
الأشخاص الذين يعيشون على دولار او أقل يومياً
I wanted him to get an experience
وأردته ان يعيش تجربة ..
in the Islamic world
داخل العالم الإسلامي
and I also wanted him to --
وأردته أيضاً أن ...
I was going there to work with a group,
كنت هنالك مع مجموعة من الاشخاص ..
do a story on a group called the Kalash,
أقوم بعمل تقرير عن أناس يدعون " كالاش "
that are a group of animists, 3,000 animists,
وهم مجموعة من الوثنيون , 3000 وثني
that live -- very small area --
يعيشون في منطقة صغيرة جداً
surrounded by Islam -- there's 3,000
محاطة بالكامل بالمسلمين ..وهؤلاء ال 3000
of these Kalash left; they're incredible people.
هم " الكالاش " الوحيدون المتبقيون ... هؤلاء الاشخاص الرائعون
So it was a great experience for him. He stayed up all night with them,
لقد كانت تجربة رائعة فعلاً , وكنت أقضي الليل بأكمله مستيقظاً بصحبتهم
drumming and dancing.
نعزف الطبول ونرقص ..
And he brought a soccer ball,
وقد أحضر إبني معه كرة قدم ..
and we had soccer every night in this little village.
وكنا نلعب بها كل ليلة في تلك القرية الصغيرة
And then we went up
ومن ثم ذهبنا ..
and met their shaman.
للقاء حكيم القبيلة
By the way, Mengatoue was the shaman
بالمناسبة " مينجاتوو" هو حكيم
of his tribe as well.
قبيلته أيضاً
And this is John Doolikahn,
وهذا هو " جون دووليكهان "
who's the shaman of the Kalash.
وهو حكيم قبيلة " كالاش "
And he's up in the mountains,
وهو يقطن في أعالي الجبال
right on the border with Afghanistan.
تحديداً على الحدود مع أفغانستان
In fact, on that other side is the area, Tora Bora,
في الحقيقة " في الطرف الآخر من هذه الحدود تقع " تورا بورا "
the area where
تلك المنطقة التي ..
Osama bin Laden's supposed to be. This is the tribal area.
يُفترض أن يكون اسامة بن لادن فيها . هذه هي منطقة القبيلة
And we watched
وقد راقبنا ..
and stayed with
وبقينا مع ..
John Doolikahn.
" جون دووليكهان "
And the shaman -- I did a whole series on shamanism,
الحكيم - كنت قد كتبت سلسلة كاملة عن الحُكماء ..
which is
والتي هي بالفعل ..
an interesting phenomenon.
ظاهرة مثيرة للاهتمام
But around the world,
تحدث حول العالم
they go into trance in different ways,
حيث يصل كل منهم الى " النشوة " بطريقته الخاصة
and in Pakistan,
وهنا في باكستان
the way they do it is they burn juniper leaves
الطريقة التي يتبعونها هي حرق أوراق " العرعر "
and they sacrifice an animal,
وتقديم أحد الحيوانات كأضحية
pour the blood of the animal on the leaves
وسكب دمائه على الاوراق
and then inhale the smoke.
ومن ثم إستنشاق الدخان
And they're all praying
وهم يصلون جميعاً
to the mountain gods
لأجل إله الجبال
as they go into trance.
ويدخلون في حالة " نشوة "
You know,
وكان هذا - كما تعلمون -
getting kids used to different realities,
هدفه تعريف الأطفال على الاشكال المختلفة من الحياة
I think, is so important. What Dan Dennett said the other day --
والذي أعتقد أنه مهم . وماقاله " دان دينيت " يوما ..
having a curriculum where they study different religions,
عن وضع منهج تعليمي لتدريس مختلف الاديان ..
just to make a mental flexibility,
لصنع مرونة " فكرية وعقلية "
give them a mental flexibility
أي لزرع المرونة الفكرية
in different belief systems --
في جميع الانظمة الدينية ..
I think this is so necessary in our world today
وهذا أعتقد انه شديد الاهمية في عالمنا اليوم
as you see these clash of beliefs taking place.
فكما ترون أن تصادم المعتقدات يحدث.
And all the security issues they cause us.
ومع كل المشاكل الامنية .. التي واجهتنا .
So, one thing we did five years ago:
لذا فأحد الامور التي قمنا بها خلال ال 5 سنوات التي مضت
we started a program that links kids
هي البدء في برنامج يصل الاطفال
in indigenous communities with kids in the United States.
في المجتمعات الاصلية مع الاطفال في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
So we first hooked up
بداية قمنا بربط ..
a spot in the Navajo Nation with a classroom in Seattle.
نقطة في شعب نافاهو مع صف مدرسي في سياتل
We now have 15 sites.
واليوم نصل بين 15 موقعاً
We have one in Kathmandu, Nepal;
فلدينا واحد في مدينة " كاثماندو " في النيبال
Dharamsala, India; Takaungu, Kenya --
و في " دهارامسلا " في الهند و " تاكونجو " في كينيا
Takaungu is one-third Christian, one-third Muslim
وبالمناسبة " تاكونجو " هي عبارة عن مدينة ثلثها مسيحيون وثلثها مسلمون
and one-third animist, the community is --
والثلث الاخير وثنيون .. وهو مجتمع كامل .
Ollantaytambo, Peru,
ومدينة " أولانتايتامبو " في البيرو
and Arctic Village, Alaska.
وقرية قطبية في ألاسكا
This is Daniel; he's one of our students
هذه صورة " دانيل " وهو أحد طلابنا
in Arctic Village, Alaska.
في القرية القطبية في الاسكا
He lives in this log cabin --
وهو يعيش في كابين طويل
no running water, no heat other than --
بدون شبكة مياه , بدون تدفئة
no windows
وبدون نوافذ
and high-speed Internet connection.
ولكن مع اتصال انترنت سريع !
And this is --
وهذا .. هذه الامور ..
I see this rolling out all over --
هذا المشروع يكبر يوما بعد يوم ..
this is our site in Ollantaytambo, Peru, four years ago,
وهنا موقع عملنا في البيرو منذ 4 سنوات
where they first saw their first computers;
عندما شاهد الاطفال لاول مرة جهاز الحاسوب
now they have computers in their classrooms.
واليوم هم يملكونه في صفوفهم
And the way we've done this --
وفي هذا المشروع نتبع طريقة حيث..
we teach digital storytelling to these kids.
نعلم الاطفال كيفية رواية قصصهم عبر هذه التقنية
And we have them tell stories about issues in their community
حيث نخبرهم بأن يروا قصص مختلفة عن قضايا مجتمعاتهم
in their community that they care about.
مجتمعاتهم التي يهتمون بها ..
And this is in Peru, where the kids told the story
وهنا في البيرو .. حيث أخبر الاولاد ..
about a river that they cleaned up.
قصة عن نهر قاموا بتنظيفه
And the way we do it is, we do it in workshops,
وكيفية قيامهم بذلك , كما اننا نقوم بورشات عمل
and we bring people who want to learn
حيث نحضر المهتمين مما يريدون تعلم
digital workflow and storytelling,
كيفية البث الالكتروني ونقل المعلومات
and have them
ونجعلهم
work with the kids.
يعملون مع الأطفال
And just this last year we've taken a group of teenagers in,
وهذا ما قمنا به العام المنصرم مع مجموعة من المراهقين
and this has worked the best.
وقد كانت النتيجة رائعة جداً
So our dream is to bring teenagers together,
لذا فحلمنا هو جمع المراهقين معاً
so they'll have a community service experience
ليندمجوا في تجارب اجتماعية ..
as well as a cross-cultural experience,
بالاضافة الى تجربة حوار الحضارات
as they teach kids in these areas
عن طريق تعليم هؤلاء الأطفال في مناطقهم
and help them build their communication infrastructure.
ومساعدتهم ببناء البُنى التحتية للاتصالات .
This is teaching Photoshop
وهنا درس تعليمي لبرنامج " الفوتو شوب "
in the Tibetan children's village in Dharamsala.
لأطفال .. لأطفال التيبت في " دهارامسلا "
We have the website, where the kids all get their homepage.
ولدينا موقع إلكتروني - حيق لكل طفل صفحته الخاصة به
This is all their movies. We've got about 60 movies
ولدينا هنا " افلام " من صنعهم , مايقارب ال 60 فلماً
that these kids have made,
التي قام الأطفال بصنعها
and they're quite incredible.
وقد كانت رائعة فعلاً
The one I want to show you --
والذي اريد ان اريكم إياه
after we get them to make the movies,
أنه بعد أن انتهينا من صناعة الأفلام
we have a night where we show the movies to the community.
قمنا بجمع اشخاص من المجتمع وعرضناها عليهم في احدى الليالي .
And this is in Takaungu --
وهذه في تاكانوجو
we've got a generator and a digital projector,
حيث نملك " مولد كهرباء " وجهاز اسقاط
and we're projecting it up against a barn,
كنا نُسقط الصورة على جدار حظيرة
and showing one of the movies that they made.
لنعرض أحد الأفلام التي قام بصنعها الأطفال
And if you get a chance, you can go to our website, and you'll see
وإذا حظيتم بالوقت يمكنكم زيارة الموقع والتعرف على هذا
the incredible work these kids do.
العمل المدهش الذي قام به هؤلاء الاطفال
The other thing:
هؤلاء الاطفال هم .. شيء آخر ..
I wanted to give indigenous people a voice.
أريد ان اعطي السكان الاصلين صوتاً
That was one of the big motivating factors.
وكان هذا احد اهم عوامل التحفيز لدي
But the other motivating factor is
ولكن العامل الآخر هو ..
the insular nature of our country.
مدى انعزالية بلدنا
National Geographic just did a Roper Study
فقد قامت " ناشيونل جيوغرفيك " بدراسة مع " روبير "
of 18 to 26 year olds
على اشخاص اعمارهم بين 18 - 26
in our country
في بلدنا
and in nine other industrialized countries.
وفي 9 دول صناعية أُخرى
It was a two million dollar study.
وقد كلفت هذه الدراسة نحو مليوني دولار
United States came in second to last
حيث جائت الولايات المتحدة في المرتبة قبل الاخيرة
in geographic knowledge.
في المعلومات الجغرافية
70 percent of the kids couldn't find
حيث لم يستطع 70% من الاطفال تحديد موقع
Afghanistan or Iraq on a map;
العراق أو افغانستان على الخريطة
60 percent couldn't find India;
و60% منهم لم يستطع إيجاد الهند
30 percent couldn't find the Pacific Ocean.
و30% لم يجد المحيط الهادىء !
And this is a study
وهذه الدراسة
that was just done a couple of years ago.
تم القيام بها منذ عامين فقط .
So what I'd like to show you now,
وأريد أن أريكم الآن
in the couple of minutes I have left,
في الدقيقتين التي مازلت أملك
is a film that a student made in Guatemala.
فلم صنعه أحد الاطفال في جواتيمالا
We just had a workshop in Guatemala.
حيث قمنا بعمل ورشة عمل هناك في جواتيمالا
A week before we got to the workshop,
قبل تلك الورشة بأسبوع واحد
a massive landslide, caused by Hurricane Stan,
حدثت انهيارات كبيرة جداً بسبب الاعصار " ستان "
last October, came in and buried
في شهر أكتوبر الماضي .. حيث عبر ودفن
600 people alive in their village.
600 شخص في قراهم ..
And this kid lived in the village --
وهذا الطفل كان يعيش في تلك القرية
he wasn't there at the time --
ولم يكن هنالك حينها ..
and this is the little movie he put together about that.
وهذا هو الفلم الذي قام بصنعه عن هذا الامر ..
And he hadn't seen a computer before
ولم يكن قد رأى جهاز كمبيوتر من قبل
we did this movie. We taught him Photoshop and --
حيث علمناه كيفية استخدام الفوتوشوب وصنعنا هذا الفلم
yeah, we can play it.
نعم .. يمكننا عرضه
This is an old Mayan funeral chant
هذه هي الانشودة الجنائزية للمايا القديمة
that he got from his grandfather.
والتي حصل عليها من جده
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
( تصفيق )